[
    {
        "question": "Which organization developed the Indian Light Tank (ILT) that recently achieved a milestone by firing rounds at a high altitude of over 4200m?",
        "options": [
            "Indian Ordnance Factory",
            "Bharat Electronics Limited and Armament Research & Development Establishment (DRDO)",
            "High Energy Materials Research Laboratory (DRDO) and Bharat Electronics Limited",
            "Combat Vehicles Research & Development Establishment (DRDO)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which indigenous UAV, delivered by Adani Defence, is equipped with NATO's STANAG 4671 certification and provides 36 hours of endurance?",
        "options": [
            "Rustom-III",
            "Heron TP",
            "Maha Ghatak II",
            "Drishti-10 Starliner",
            "None of the Above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "In a significant step toward bolstering India\u2019s defence capabilities and promoting the \u2018Aatmanirbhar Bharat\u2019 initiative, the Ministry of Defence (MoD) has signed a contract with Hindustan Aeronautics Ltd (HAL) for the procurement of 12 Su-30MKI aircraft. What is the percentage of homegrown content in the Su-30MKI aircraft being procured?",
        "options": [
            "50%",
            "55.2%",
            "60%",
            "62.6%",
            "75.6%"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company has secured \u20b9136-crore contract to supply indigenously designed High Mobility Vehicles (HMVs) 8\u00d78?",
        "options": [
            "Hindustan Aeronautics Limited",
            "Bharat Heavy Electricals Limited",
            "BEML Limited",
            "Tata Advanced Systems",
            "Bharat Electronics Limited"
        ],
        "answer": "BEML Limited"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Russian-built multi-role stealth-guided missile frigate INS Tushil was commissioned into the Indian Navy at the Yantar Shipyard in Kaliningrad, Russia. What is unique about the construction of INS Tushil?",
        "options": [
            "It is the first Indian-built stealth frigate.",
            "It is the seventh ship of Project 1135.6, built under an India-Russia collaboration.",
            "It is a nuclear-powered frigate built by Baltiysky Zawod.",
            "It is the first ship constructed under the Atmanirbhar Bharat initiative.",
            "It is the first ship to feature entirely indigenous weaponry."
        ],
        "answer": "It is the seventh ship of Project 1135.6, built under an India-Russia collaboration."
    },
    {
        "question": "In December 2024, what is the name of the unmanned surface vessel handed over by GRSE to DRDO?",
        "options": [
            "Jalveer",
            "Jaldoot",
            "Jalrakshak",
            "Jalpari",
            "Jalvahan"
        ],
        "answer": "Jaldoot"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country has approved a possible $1.17 billion deal to sell India support equipment for MH-60R multi-role helicopters under its Foreign Military Sales programme?",
        "options": [
            "USA",
            "Russia",
            "France",
            "China",
            "Australia"
        ],
        "answer": "USA"
    },
    {
        "question": "Israel approved a $11.13 million plan to expand settlements in the ___________, citing border security concerns after Syria's Assad regime's fall.",
        "options": [
            "West Bank",
            "Gaza Strip",
            "Golan Heights",
            "Jerusalem",
            "Syria"
        ],
        "answer": "Golan Heights"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Indian Navy's latest survey ship, Nirdeshak, will be commissioned at which location?",
        "options": [
            "Mumbai",
            "Chennai",
            "Kochi",
            "Visakhapatnam",
            "Kolkata"
        ],
        "answer": "Visakhapatnam"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country did INS Sarvekshak conduct a joint hydrographic survey with, focusing on maritime infrastructure, resource management, and coastal planning?",
        "options": [
            "India",
            "Mauritius",
            "Maldives",
            "Sri Lanka",
            "Madagascar"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "The hypersonic missile powered by a scramjet engine will travel above what speed?",
        "options": [
            "Mach 2",
            "Mach 3",
            "Mach 4",
            "Mach 5",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Mach 5"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the special exercise started by BSF to thwart infiltration attempts during winter on the Indo-Pak border in Jaisalmer?",
        "options": [
            "Operation Sard Hawa",
            "Operation Garam Hawa",
            "Operation Winter Shield",
            "Operation Desert Vigil",
            "Operation Atmosphere Blanket"
        ],
        "answer": "Operation Sard Hawa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was the seventh Missile Cum Ammunition Barge (LSAM 14) launched?",
        "options": [
            "Visakhapatnam",
            "Kochi",
            "Pune",
            "Mira Bhayandar",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Mira Bhayandar"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the primary aim of the European Space Agency's (ESA) Proba-3 mission, which will be launched by ISRO via PSLV-C59?",
        "options": [
            "To study Earth's atmospheric changes",
            "To explore the Sun's corona",
            "To monitor asteroids near Earth",
            "To test satellite communication technologies",
            "None of the Above"
        ],
        "answer": "To explore the Sun's corona"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country successfully tested the Long-Range Hypersonic Weapon (LRHW) in 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Russia",
            "China",
            "United States",
            "India",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "United States"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which manufacturer unveiled the BD475-2 Dozer, India's biggest and most advanced crawler dozer?",
        "options": [
            "BEML",
            "Larsen & Toubro",
            "BHEL",
            "Mahindra",
            "BEL"
        ],
        "answer": "BEML"
    },
    {
        "question": "How much is the deal worth that the Ministry of Defence signed to boost the army's firepower?",
        "options": [
            "\u20b95,000 crore",
            "\u20b912,000 crore",
            "\u20b915,000 crore",
            "\u20b910,000 crore",
            "\u20b920,000 crore"
        ],
        "answer": "\u20b910,000 crore"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the upgraded Hindustan Jet Trainer (HJT) 36 unveiled by HAL at Aero India 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Vijay",
            "Yashas",
            "Prithvi",
            "Shakti",
            "Chakra"
        ],
        "answer": "Yashas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two countries are enhancing cooperation in maintaining Sukhoi-30 (Su-30) combat aircraft fleets?",
        "options": [
            "India and Russia",
            "India and China",
            "India and France",
            "India and Malaysia",
            "India and Pakistan"
        ],
        "answer": "India and Malaysia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization released the redefined and augmented Research Verticals & Thrust Areas to enhance research focus in defense technology?",
        "options": [
            "Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR)",
            "Defence Research and Development Organisation (DRDO)",
            "National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA)",
            "Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the full form of VSHORAD in the context of DRDO's missile system?",
        "options": [
            "Very Small High-Output Radar Air Defence",
            "Very Short-Range Air Defence",
            "Variable Spectrum High-Range Air Defence",
            "Vertical Strike Hypersonic Operational Radar Air Defence",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two companies have formed a joint venture for manufacturing the HAMMER precision-guided weapon in India?",
        "options": [
            "Safran Electronics & Defense and Boeing",
            "Bharat Electronics Limited (BEL) and Lockheed Martin",
            "Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL) and Safran Electronics & Defense",
            "Bharat Electronics Limited (BEL) and Safran Electronics & Defense",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Bharat Electronics Limited (BEL) and Safran Electronics & Defense"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company partnered with Garuda Aerospace to develop indigenous UAVs at Aero India 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Tata Elxsi",
            "Hindustan Aeronautics Limited",
            "Bharat Electronics Limited",
            "Adani Defence & Aerospace",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which defense system is being collaborated on between Swedish defense firm Saab and Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL) as per their recent MoU?",
        "options": [
            "Combat Management System",
            "Laser Warning System (LWS-310)",
            "Radar Warning System",
            "Anti-Missile Defense System",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Laser Warning System (LWS-310)"
    },
    {
        "question": "On January 1, 2025, which organization celebrated its 67th Foundation Day in New Delhi?",
        "options": [
            "Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)",
            "Defence Research and Development Organisation (DRDO)",
            "Bharat Electronics Limited (BEL)",
            "Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL)",
            "Bhabha Atomic Research Centre (BARC)"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which app was launched by Defence Minister Rajnath Singh during the 77th Army Day celebrations to promote battlefield tourism?",
        "options": [
            "Bharat Raksha App",
            "Military Heritage App",
            "Bharat Ranbhoomi Darshan App",
            "Siachen War Memorial App",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Nag Mk 2, a _____-generation Fire-and-Forget Anti-Tank Guided Missile, successfully completed field trials at Pokhran Field Range, achieving targets at both maximum and minimum ranges.",
        "options": [
            "2nd",
            "3rd",
            "4th",
            "5th",
            "6th"
        ],
        "answer": "3rd"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which year has the Ministry of Defence designated as the 'Year of Reforms' to modernize the Armed Forces?",
        "options": [
            "2023",
            "2024",
            "2025",
            "2026",
            "2027"
        ],
        "answer": "2025"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the advanced battlefield surveillance system launched by Defence Minister Rajnath Singh in January 2025 to boost the Indian Army's reconnaissance capabilities?",
        "options": [
            "ABHAY",
            "SANJAY",
            "VAJRA",
            "SATARK",
            "SAMYAK"
        ],
        "answer": "SANJAY"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Indian Navy commissioned its latest multi-role stealth-guided missile frigate, INS Tushil. Which of the following statement/statements is/are correct?\n1 - Guided missile frigate INS Tushil (F 70) was commissioned into the Indian Navy at Kaliningrad, Russia, by Defence Minister Rajnath Singh.\n2 - The INS Tushil is an upgraded Krivak-III class frigate under Project 1135.6.\n3 - The INS Tushil joined the \"Sword Arm of the Indian Navy\", the Western Fleet, under the Western Naval Command.",
        "options": [
            "Only 1",
            "Only 2 and 3",
            "Only 1 and 3",
            "All of the above are correct.",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above are correct."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which project do INS Vaghsheer belong to?",
        "options": [
            "Project 75",
            "Project B",
            "Project 15B",
            "None of the above",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Project 75"
    }
]